<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/pilots/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-12-30T16:09:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/pilots/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">UBI Center | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Analyzing universal basic income policies with open-source research</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The UBI Center’s 2020 year in review</title>
      <link href="/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The UBI Center’s 2020 year in review" />
      <published>2021-01-01T07:14:31+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-01T07:14:31+00:00</updated>
      <id>/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review">&lt;h4 id=&quot;our-work-studies-from-other-researchers-and-the-biggest-ubi-news-from-the-pastyear&quot;&gt;Our work, studies from other researchers, and the biggest UBI news from the past year&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has been a devastating year. Covid-19 has killed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/&quot;&gt;nearly two million people&lt;/a&gt; worldwide, thrown &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/feature/2020/10/07/global-action-urgently-needed-to-halt-historic-threats-to-poverty-reduction&quot;&gt;tens of millions&lt;/a&gt; into extreme poverty, and disrupted virtually every aspect of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has also changed perceptions of social protection programs. With millions unable to work safely, populations are more open to unconditional cash transfers, and governments have delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers have continued to investigate how societies could adopt universal basic income policies, and fueled by our biggest growth year (we now have &lt;a href=&quot;about/our-team&quot;&gt;ten researchers&lt;/a&gt;), we’ve contributed with policy simulations and evidence reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following up on our &lt;a href=&quot;what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019&quot;&gt;2019 review&lt;/a&gt;, this post summarizes our work from the past year, along with studies from other researchers and the biggest UBI news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ubi-centerresearch&quot;&gt;UBI Center research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;policy-simulation&quot;&gt;Policy simulation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bread-and-butter simulations of UBI policy became more targeted, robust, and policy-relevant throughout 2020. Our simulations showed how UBI would shrink &lt;a href=&quot;how-universal-basic-income-would-affect-the-black-white-poverty-and-wealth-gaps&quot;&gt;black-white poverty and wealth gaps&lt;/a&gt;, how it would affect &lt;a href=&quot;ada30&quot;&gt;people with disabilities&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;indigenous&quot;&gt;Indigenous Americans&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;veterans&quot;&gt;Veterans&lt;/a&gt;, and how a &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;child allowance&lt;/a&gt; would cut child poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-0.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first paper of the Covid era showed how different UBI policy designs could &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/viewer?url=https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/covid19/master/UBI_for_Covid_19.pdf&quot;&gt;stabilize the poverty rate&lt;/a&gt; amid income-lowering recessions, and our latest analysis showed how replacing our existing tax code with a &lt;a href=&quot;us-flat-tax&quot;&gt;flat income tax&lt;/a&gt; could be made progressive with a UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-1.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also compared UBI to other policies (given a fixed budget), finding that it would be more progressive than &lt;a href=&quot;student-debt&quot;&gt;canceling student debt&lt;/a&gt;, and likely more progressive than expanding additional US &lt;a href=&quot;http://covid.ubicenter.org/fpuc&quot;&gt;unemployment benefits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-research&quot;&gt;Other research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, we expanded our research portfolio beyond policy simulation to other topics related to UBI. We produced &lt;a href=&quot;canada-homelessness-experiment&quot;&gt;novel analyses&lt;/a&gt; and context of a cash transfer experiment targeting Canadians experiencing homelessness. To inform Democratic primaries, we &lt;a href=&quot;basic-income-plans-from-congressional-candidates-mike-broihier-and-suraj-patel&quot;&gt;summarized&lt;/a&gt; candidates’ stances on UBI. And we tracked and summarized all 27 emergency cash transfer proposals in the US (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thebalance.com/pandemic-tests-universal-basic-income-5078483&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; of our tracker in The Balance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-2.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also integrated deeper non-simulation analysis into simulation projects. Our &lt;a href=&quot;http://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical&quot;&gt;child allowance project&lt;/a&gt; summarized dozens of papers on the impacts of child poverty, while our &lt;a href=&quot;us-flat-tax&quot;&gt;flat tax project&lt;/a&gt; included original statistical analysis of tax and transfer policies associated with inequality reduction among OECD countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-3.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-source-contributions&quot;&gt;Open source contributions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re the first and only economic policy think tank to open-source all of our work, and we take pride in using and contributing to open source software for economic policy research. This year, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.org&quot;&gt;Policy Simulation Library&lt;/a&gt; accepted two of our Python packages — &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.github.io/openfisca-uk&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;microdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;for analyzing survey data, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pslmodels.github.io/openfisca-uk&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;openfisca-uk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for simulating UK economic policy — to its catalog, adding two of our staff to its leadership council. We also created new incubating models to work with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/scf&quot;&gt;US Survey of Consumer Finances&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nikhilwoodruff/frs&quot;&gt;UK Family Resources Survey&lt;/a&gt;. Our researchers contributed to several open source projects on GitHub, from improving documentation in PSL’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/Tax-Calculator/pull/2420&quot;&gt;Tax-Calculator&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PSLmodels/OG-USA/pull/634&quot;&gt;OG-USA&lt;/a&gt; economic models to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mwburke/stargazer/pull/53&quot;&gt;enhancing&lt;/a&gt; Python’s support for producing publication-grade regression tables. Finally, we made our own research more open and reproducible by moving most content to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyterbook.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter-Book&lt;/a&gt;, which shows hideable code within the interactive web document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outreach&quot;&gt;Outreach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shared our research in numerous forums: op-eds in The Hill on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/514672-would-basic-income-be-better-than-additional-unemployment-benefits&quot;&gt;unemployment benefit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/opinion/education/529953-child-allowance-would-boost-gdp&quot;&gt;child allowance&lt;/a&gt; analyses; presentations at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1456wwH-W24gXrfOhvDRCHyqZRhelUx64XTrXj-HQRYw/edit#slide=id.g6293382480_0_338&quot;&gt;Tax Economists Forum&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WoHnOqFu6KQ&quot;&gt;PyData Global&lt;/a&gt; conference, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/lL17YLCGSxs&quot;&gt;Social Giving&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MtDjRauJmE8&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wCK_xw0IMDs&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;my-nerds-for-humanity-interview-on-basic-income&quot;&gt;channels&lt;/a&gt;. We also launched our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://us3.campaign-archive.com/home/?u=ffee9994a6979a91e881b8c13&amp;amp;id=938462295c&quot;&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt; and YouTube &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCg0PhP-7kCHtAjcVc7XfTfA&quot;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;plans-for2021&quot;&gt;Plans for 2021&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2021 promises to be an even bigger year, with upcoming simulations of UBI in the UK, benchmarks of UBI against competing policies, macroeconomic and behavioral effects, interactive tools, events and partnerships, a new website, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;external-research&quot;&gt;External research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reviews-andtools&quot;&gt;Reviews and tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/uploads/Umbrella%20Review%20BI_final.pdf&quot;&gt;Stanford Basic Income Lab UBI study cross-synthesis&lt;/a&gt; affirmed that UBI-type programs alleviate poverty, improve health and education outcomes, while having minimal effects on labour market participation. It nominated understanding of the “tradeoffs between UBI and other programs,” and particularly the impact of “financing a UBI through new revenue streams or diversions from existing programs” as a key gap in the existing research — precisely the gap our research aims to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cash transfer evidence base also became more navigable with the creation of new tools to access studies that address the impact of cash transfer. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/&quot;&gt;Basic Income Lab&lt;/a&gt; expanded its platform, providing new &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincome.stanford.edu/research/ubi-visualization/&quot;&gt;visualizations&lt;/a&gt; that allow users to dive into studies related to UBIs categorized by outcome. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/cash-research-explorer/&quot;&gt;Cash Research Explorer&lt;/a&gt; that enables users to filter and sort a large database of existing cash transfer studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;policy-simulations&quot;&gt;Policy simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We welcomed not being the only UBI simulators in town, with studies on various policy designs being conducted around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, Columbia University’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.povertycenter.columbia.edu/&quot;&gt;Center on Poverty &amp;amp; Social Policy&lt;/a&gt; released a series of policy briefs on how a guaranteed income would affect poverty, comparing recent policy proposals and addressing child inclusion in a carbon tax and universal dividend program. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/up-front/2020/01/30/how-a-vat-could-tax-the-rich-and-pay-for-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;simulation from Brookings&lt;/a&gt; found 10% VAT could reduce the debt by $2.9 trillion over 10 years, boost means-tested programs and Social Security, and provide a UBI at 20% of the poverty line, raising bottom-quintile income by 17%. And a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27351&quot;&gt;dynamic macro model&lt;/a&gt; found that most Americans would prefer UBI today, but future generations would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1035304620964272&quot;&gt;Australian study&lt;/a&gt; found that an “affluence-tested” UBI would reduce inequality and poverty to levels similar to Nordic welfare states, requiring an increase in taxation to approximately the OECD average. Other simulations in &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s41825-017-0007-2&quot;&gt;Gulf states&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://works.bepress.com/widerquist/119/&quot;&gt;the UK&lt;/a&gt; showed similarly egalitarian results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal taxation papers continued to study policies that rebate excess revenue as UBI. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28098&quot;&gt;One such paper&lt;/a&gt; found that optimal tax rates and welfare rise when incorporating uncertainty around labor responses, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27622&quot;&gt;another from NBER&lt;/a&gt; found that “a uniform flat tax on capital and labor income combined with a lump-sum transfer is nearly optimal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resilience-and-adherence-covid-19&quot;&gt;Resilience and adherence: COVID-19&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a difficult year in which COVID-19 brought economies around the world to a standstill, we learned more about how cash transfers can create resilience to income shocks. The continuation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt;’s UBI experiment in Kenya during the COVID-19 crisis offered the opportunity to estimate the impact of unconditional cash transfers to poor families. As the first true UBI experiment in history — guaranteeing payments that meet basic needs for each member of randomly selected villages for up to 12 years — its first results deserve special attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://econweb.ucsd.edu/~pniehaus/papers/ubi_covid.pdf&quot;&gt;Banerjee et al.&lt;/a&gt; found that the UBI, which began in 2016, significantly reduced recipient hunger, sickness and depression in spite of the pandemic, though with modest effect sizes. It also reduced hospital visits and decreased social interactions, indicating that access to a UBI offered people a greater capacity to follow public health recommendations about social distancing and thereby likely reduced contagion rates. While recipients lost the income gains from starting non-agricultural enterprises during the pandemic, they suffered smaller increases in hunger, indicating that the UBI induced recipients to accept more income risk by mitigating the effects of adverse income shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mental-health&quot;&gt;Mental health&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, numerous studies shed light on how cash transfers can reduce stress, improve self-reported well-being and enable participants to make more rational long-term economic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finland’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kela.fi/web/en/news-archive/-/asset_publisher/lN08GY2nIrZo/content/results-of-the-basic-income-experiment-small-employment-effects-better-perceived-economic-security-and-mental-wellbeing&quot;&gt;basic income experiment&lt;/a&gt;, which was carried out in 2017–18, reported this year that basic income recipients were more satisfied with their lives, experienced less mental strain and had a more positive perception of their economic welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a developing context, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jae/advance-article/doi/10.1093/jae/ejaa010/6015888&quot;&gt;Molotsky and Handa&lt;/a&gt; found that national cash transfers in Malawi reduced stress and improved positive affect among recipients; these psychological effects directly impacted on economic decision-making, encouraging recipients to make more long term decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28106&quot;&gt;Haushofer et al., 2020b&lt;/a&gt; found that cash transfers in rural Kenya outperformed more costly psychotherapy programs both in economic and psychological well-being outcomes, and that a combination of cash transfers and psychotherapy was no more effective than cash alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0304387818310289?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;Haushofer et al., 2020a&lt;/a&gt; found that in Nairobi, free health insurance outperformed a uniform cash transfer of the same value in reducing self-reported stress and cortisol levels, though the most conservative statistical bounds render the difference statistically insignificant. It found no effect of either program on other economic and health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large-scale &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.happierlivesinstitute.org/uploads/1/0/9/9/109970865/cash_transfer_meta-analysis_working_paper_1.53.pdf&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; found that cash transfers improved self-reported subjective well-being and mental health and that the higher the transfer, the greater the impact. Unconditional cash transfers outperformed conditional cash transfers. And a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6522/eaay0214?rss%253D1=&quot;&gt;review in Science Magazine&lt;/a&gt; found that “cash transfers and broader antipoverty programs reduce depression and anxiety in randomized trials […] poverty experienced in childhood and in utero [results] in impaired cognitive development and adult mental illness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-effects-of-cash-transfers&quot;&gt;Other effects of cash transfers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voluminous literature on cash transfers continued to grow rapidly in 2020. Here are a sample of influential papers from the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w28074/w28074.pdf&quot;&gt;multifaceted intervention&lt;/a&gt; that included a cash transfer for 30 to 40 weeks improved consumption, food security, income, and health for up to a decade. In Mexico, cash transfers &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1uYloKO69ESDXHIU5n-1XmiLK3APrMs0_/view&quot;&gt;halved homicides&lt;/a&gt; on hot days by reducing stress and increasing air conditioning. In Rwanda, cash transfers &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.01749&quot;&gt;outperformed&lt;/a&gt; a USAID workforce readiness program on key outcomes like income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, the 1990s retraction of cash assistance to poor mothers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28077&quot;&gt;worsened child-parent interactions&lt;/a&gt; (the effect was not traced to changes in the mother’s labor supply). The Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w26712&quot;&gt;increased fertility&lt;/a&gt; (births per woman) by 13 percent after its introduction, mostly among women aged 20 to 44.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conditionality-and-targeting&quot;&gt;Conditionality and targeting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0305750X20300024#f0010&quot;&gt;New evidence&lt;/a&gt; from the Kenya Cash Transfer Programme for Orphans and Vulnerable Children for at-risk children shows that enforcing compliance with health conditions with monitoring and fines doesn’t improve program effectiveness compared to ‘labelling’ transfers — providing suggestions for how recipients should use transfers. The study also showed that fines had regressive impacts. Among the poorest transfer recipients, fines for noncompliance were associated with a significant decline in non-food consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers also quantified the cost of &lt;a href=&quot;https://wagner.nyu.edu/impact/research/publications/program-recertification-costs-evidence-snap&quot;&gt;administrative burdens&lt;/a&gt; for SNAP recipients in the US, and the New York Times centered this research in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/01/28/upshot/administrative-burden-quiz.html&quot;&gt;interactive story&lt;/a&gt;. The Jain Family Institute published two papers in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jainfamilyinstitute.org/projects/from-idea-to-reality-the-future-of-guaranteed-income/&quot;&gt;series on guaranteed income&lt;/a&gt;, describing implementation of guaranteed income in the US and a framework for considering what programs the guaranteed income could suitably replace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;polls&quot;&gt;Polls&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pollsters asked people from all over the world how they felt about UBI and cash transfers, and the timing of these polls showed how Covid-19 affected sentiments toward the welfare state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first polls came from the US, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheUBICenter/status/1245575691082428423&quot;&gt;in February&lt;/a&gt;, 63% of people aged 18–36 supported a universal basic income of $1,000 per month for adults. Data for Progress &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2020/3/19/voters-want-the-government-to-send-everyone-1000&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that net support for sending each American a check for $1,000 rose from -15 to +32 between March 2 and March 17, when the gravity of the pandemic became apparent. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/3/21/voters-support-a-robust-cash-payment&quot;&gt;Also in March&lt;/a&gt;, Data for Progress found that Americans prefer ongoing payments to one-time payments by a 38-point margin, and between monthly payments of (a) $2,000/adult + $1,000/child and (b) $1,000/adult, voters prefer the larger amount by a 15-point margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polls outside the US found majority support for the policy, too. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://eupinions.eu/de/text/in-crisis-europeans-support-radical-positions&quot;&gt;March poll&lt;/a&gt; found that 71% of Europeans support UBI; an &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/5y7qpjzd6v/NEON_CoronavirusClimate_200417_W.pdf&quot;&gt;April poll&lt;/a&gt; found that 51% of Brits supported it; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.probe-research.com/polls/manitobans-support-universal-basic-income-higher-taxes-high-income-earners-and-larger&quot;&gt;also in April&lt;/a&gt;, 62% of Manitoba, Canada residents supported UBI; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/news/2020-12-11/survey-says-most-australians-welcome-universal-basic-income/12970924&quot;&gt;as of October&lt;/a&gt;, 58% of Australians supported it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calls-forubi&quot;&gt;Calls for UBI&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government leaders and other influential people and organizations called for UBI pilots and policies, especially relating to (but not limited to) the Covid-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most forceful voices came from the UK. The Liberal Democrats (the third largest party, which received &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Results_breakdown_of_the_2019_United_Kingdom_general_election&quot;&gt;12 percent of votes&lt;/a&gt; in 2019) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libdems.org.uk/a20-ubi&quot;&gt;endorsed UBI&lt;/a&gt; in September, and in October, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubilabnetwork.org/letter-to-rishi-sunak&quot;&gt;over 500 MPs, peers and councillors&lt;/a&gt; requested that the Chancellor support UBI trials. Throughout the year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/oct/31/covid-job-losses-lead-mps-to-call-for-trials-of-universal-basic-income&quot;&gt;several councils&lt;/a&gt; campaigned to launch UBI pilots in their areas, including Liverpool, Brighton, Leeds, Norwich and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaders in Canada have been similarly enthusiastic. Canada has a rich history of unconditional cash transfers: they created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200624-canadas-forgotten-universal-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;Mincome experiment&lt;/a&gt; in the 1970s, a UBI pilot in the province of Ontario (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/economy/making-sense/ontario-is-canceling-its-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;prematurely cancelled&lt;/a&gt; in 2019), a generous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubiworks.ca/ccb&quot;&gt;child benefit&lt;/a&gt;, and the CERB program providing CAD 2,000 (USD 1,570) per month through September to people who’d lost employment due to Covid-19. In July, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalpost.com/news/politics/now-is-the-time-to-bring-a-basic-income-program-to-canada-says-b-c-senator-but-the-pilot-project-could-cost-100-million&quot;&gt;British Columbia Senator Yuen Pau&lt;/a&gt; Woo suggested testing UBI, and in the same month, the Senate national finance committee released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sencanada.ca/en/info-page/parl-43-1/nffn-covid-19-relief-in-times-of-crisis/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; highlighting the need for UBI. In September, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2020/09/15/coalition-calls-on-federal-liberals-to-bring-in-a-basic-income-to-address-gender-inequity.html&quot;&gt;a coalition&lt;/a&gt; of nearly 4,000 individuals and organizations called on the federal government to work toward UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, several members of Congress called for one-time and recurring unconditional payments amid Covid-19 (see our &lt;a href=&quot;http://covid19tracker.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;tracker&lt;/a&gt;), including a proposal for $2,000 monthly checks per person from Senator Bernie Sanders and Vice President-elect Kamala Harris. The one-time relief payments of $1,200 from March were renewed at $600 in the December bill, along with flat payments of $300 per week for unemployed people (down from $600 from April through July). The governor of Alaska also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alaskapublic.org/2020/12/14/dunleavy-proposes-nearly-5000-in-dividends-for-alaskans-cuts-other-state-spending/&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; increasing the Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend from its normal value of $1,000-$3,000 to $5,000 due to the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-UBI US voices were elevated in 2021, too. In April, Jack Dorsey created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/recode/2020/4/7/21212757/coronavirus-jack-dorsey-charity-billion-llc&quot;&gt;$1 billion philanthropic fund&lt;/a&gt; from his holdings in Square; the fund has since grown to $3.7 billion, of which he’s spent $330 million, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uT6Tw0lrYMj9YSQpkMAyf_i31Urf0IWW5wIJ76Rckv8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;$44 million&lt;/a&gt; for UBI pilots. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1286675223434141697&quot;&gt;Pro-UBI&lt;/a&gt; Elon Musk became the world’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/sergeiklebnikov/2020/12/08/elon-musk-passes-bernard-arnault-to-become-the-worlds-second-richest-person/?sh=ab0da895cb0d&quot;&gt;second wealthiest person&lt;/a&gt; in December. Andrew Yang, who centered his presidential campaign on UBI (we &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/distributional-analysis-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-d8dab818bf1b&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/a-revenue-neutral-version-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-d7d517dbeeea&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ubicenter/why-some-low-income-people-come-out-behind-in-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend-c95d0f1cc433&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://plans.ubicenter.org&quot;&gt;calculator&lt;/a&gt; on his plan in 2019), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/02/11/politics/andrew-yang-ends-2020-presidential-campaign/index.html&quot;&gt;ended his presidential campaign&lt;/a&gt; in February, but he is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/531337-poll-finds-andrew-yang-favored-for-new-york-city-mayor&quot;&gt;now the favorite&lt;/a&gt; for New York City’s 2021 mayoral race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaders in various other countries have supported UBI as well. In March, one of Australia’s largest unions &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-8154513/Australian-union-pushes-universal-income-740-week.html&quot;&gt;called for a guaranteed income&lt;/a&gt; throughout the pandemic, structured as a job guarantee plus AUD 740 (USD 725) per week for people who don’t participate in the job guarantee program. In South Africa, the governing party &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.groundup.org.za/media/uploads/documents/anc_nec_stsc_big-1.pdf&quot;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; the need for a UBI, but plans for a 2020 policy were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-safrica-economy-universalincomegrant/south-africa-will-not-have-universal-basic-income-grant-this-year-minister-says-idUSKCN24W2WK&quot;&gt;scrapped in July&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, the United Nations &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cepal.org/en/publications/45544-social-challenge-times-covid-19&quot;&gt;Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean&lt;/a&gt; and UN Development Program’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.un.org/en/story/2020/05/1063312&quot;&gt;Asia-Pacific bureau&lt;/a&gt; have called for UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;guaranteed-income-initiatives&quot;&gt;Guaranteed income initiatives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to one-time payments and ongoing payments to unemployed people like those in the US and Canada, several governments and nonprofits are sending regular cash payments to broad sets of people without requiring work history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayorsforagi.org/&quot;&gt;Mayors for a Guaranteed Income&lt;/a&gt; — which now includes over 30 mayors — is driving a number of new philanthropically-funded guaranteed income pilots, including in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2020-10-18/800-compton-residents-to-get&quot;&gt;Compton&lt;/a&gt;, and established the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sp2.upenn.edu/center-for-guaranteed-income-research-recently-launched/&quot;&gt;Center for Guaranteed Income Research&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Pennsylvania. &lt;a href=&quot;https://reason.com/2020/10/13/san-francisco-will-pay-artists-1000-a-month-in-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://basicincometoday.com/long-beach-moves-ahead-with-guaranteed-basic-income-for-some-artists/&quot;&gt;Long Beach&lt;/a&gt; will also both give basic incomes to artists (see our comments in coverage of the San Francisco program). But the nonprofit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/covid-19/us/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; has already distributed the most — since March, they’ve transferred $1,000 to each of 134,000 SNAP recipients, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/GiveDirectly-End-of-Year-Update.pdf?utm_source=email&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=202012eoyupdatematch&amp;amp;utm_content=eoy_update&quot;&gt;99% efficiency&lt;/a&gt; and an average of two days between enrollment and first payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly also delivered transfers to over 500,000 recipients outside the US, creating new contact-free payment models and adding new programs. For example, they provided USAID-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liberianobserver.com/news/givedirectly-educational-stipends-for-12th-graders-writing-the-wassce-exam/&quot;&gt;educational stipends&lt;/a&gt; of $50 to 37,000 12th-graders in every high school in Liberia, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90585079/how-givedirectly-is-finding-the-poorest-people-in-the-world-and-sending-them-cash&quot;&gt;applied machine learning&lt;/a&gt; to identify and pay extremely poor households in Togo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-brazil-economics/brazils-government-backs-new-basic-income-payments-to-poor-idUKKBN26J381&quot;&gt;expanding&lt;/a&gt; its Bolsa Familia cash transfer into a new program called Renda Cidada (“citizen income”), and Bogota, Colombia, is giving cash and food aid to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-world-ahead/2020/11/17/claudia-lopez-on-the-acceleration-of-social-innovation&quot;&gt;over 700,000 households&lt;/a&gt;. Spain introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/economy/2020/5/30/spain-introduces-basic-income-scheme-to-tackle-poverty&quot;&gt;minimum income program&lt;/a&gt; that intended to benefit over 2 million individuals, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/news/spain-struggles-to-put-in-place-basic-income-scheme-01598763004&quot;&gt;implementation challenges&lt;/a&gt; are slowing it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-01-01-ubi-centers-2020-year-in-review-4.png#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On most measures, 2021 has a low bar to clear to outdo 2020. Given this array of studies, UBI research might not be one of those measures, but we expect even more simulations, randomized controlled trials, meta-analyses, and new programs to inform UBI policy design and how UBI compares to the status quo and alternatives. To follow our research on these fronts, subscribe to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://ubicenter.us3.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=ffee9994a6979a91e881b8c13&amp;amp;id=938462295c&quot;&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt; or follow us on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UBI Center team&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;max&quot;, &quot;ankit&quot;, &quot;john&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="pilots" />
      
        <category term="external research" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We joined scholars around the world in accelerating UBI research.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What a Canadian experiment tells us about cash transfers and homelessness</title>
      <link href="/canada-homelessness-experiment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What a Canadian experiment tells us about cash transfers and homelessness" />
      <published>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/canada-homelessness-experiment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/canada-homelessness-experiment">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://homelesshub.ca/sites/default/files/SOHC16_final_20Oct2016.pdf&quot;&gt;35,000 Canadians&lt;/a&gt; experience homelessness each night, violating their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Housing/Pages/Homelessnessandhumanrights.aspx&quot;&gt;right to adequate housing&lt;/a&gt; and threatening their &lt;a href=&quot;https://depts.washington.edu/triolive/quest/2007/TTQ07033/effects.html#:~:text=Their%20health%20gets%20worse%20from,Cardio%2DRespiratory%20diseases&quot;&gt;health, safety&lt;/a&gt; and access to &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.3102/0013189X12468210?casa_token=YsJRZhavl9EAAAAA:iKO6XaWu6oNbDgcRzw3Tml-_m6mHEYmRWGY48rzXTStFpmBEWzqa1L_euQoV8WXYkrwZ8vxj-KGMGQ&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;. The Covid-19 pandemic exacerbates the issue, given &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7206983/&quot;&gt;crowded living conditions and comorbidities&lt;/a&gt;, and the Canadian government has taken new steps to address it, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-could-shelter-hotels-be-a-model-for-addressing-homelessness/&quot;&gt;moving people experiencing homelessness into hotels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the pandemic, a Vancouver nonprofit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://forsocialchange.org/&quot;&gt;Foundations for Social Change&lt;/a&gt;, worked with the University of British Columbia to test a novel homelessness intervention: &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5f07a92f21d34b403c788e05/t/5f751297fcfe7968a6a957a8/1601507995038/2020_09_30_FSC_Statement_of_Impact_w_Expansion.pdf&quot;&gt;unconditional cash transfers&lt;/a&gt;. In spring 2018, their &lt;a href=&quot;https://forsocialchange.org/new-leaf-project-overview&quot;&gt;New Leaf Project&lt;/a&gt; (NLP) granted a lump sum cash transfer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britishcolumbia.ca/invest/communities/british-columbia/lower-mainland-southwest/&quot;&gt;Lower Mainland&lt;/a&gt; residents experiencing homelessness, and compared their outcomes to a control group. While some questions remain, the findings reveal that unconditional cash transfers, which are otherwise shown to improve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cochranelibrary.com/cdsr/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD011135.pub2/full&quot;&gt;health&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1570677X18303575&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;, and other outcomes, offer potential to reduce homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;study-overview&quot;&gt;Study overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NLP selected 115 long-term residents or citizens of Canada aged 19 to 64 who had experienced homelessness within the previous six months. This group is fairly representative of Canada’s homeless population, given only about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homelesshub.ca/about-homelessness/homelessness-101/how-many-people-are-homeless-canada&quot;&gt;10 percent&lt;/a&gt; of people experiencing homelessness in a year were homeless for more than a month, and about &lt;a href=&quot;https://homelesshub.ca/sites/default/files/SOHC16_final_20Oct2016.pdf&quot;&gt;four percent&lt;/a&gt; are aged 65 or older. People with severe substance abuse or mental health disorders were ineligible for NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the experiment, NLP deposited CAD 7,500&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cad&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cad&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; into the bank accounts of 50 participants, randomly selected from the full group of 115. Each cash recipient was also provided access to workshops, and 25 also had access to coaching. Of the 65 who did not receive cash, 19 were provided access to workshops and coaching, while the other 46 were not.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:unbalanced&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:unbalanced&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Workshops focused on the development of a personal financial plan and self-affirmation exercises, and the coaching was offered for six months, aiming to develop and sustain life skills and strategies. Researchers tracked participants over twelve months, filling out questionnaires at one, three, six, nine and twelve months and open-ended qualitative interviews at six and twelve months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button1&quot; onclick=&quot;f1()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_1&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import pandas as pd
import plotly.express as px

design = pd.DataFrame(
    {
        &quot;Workshop&quot;: [25, 0],
        &quot;Workshop + coaching&quot;: [25, 19],
        &quot;Neither&quot;: [0, 46]
    },
    index=[&quot;Cash&quot;, &quot;No cash&quot;],
)
design
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f1() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_1&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button1&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset1&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/canada-homelessness-experiment/2020-12-14-canada-homelessness-experiment-asset-1.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spending&quot;&gt;Spending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cash group spent an average of CAD 426 per month more than the non cash group over the course of the year. This amounts to 42 percent more than the non-cash group, or 6 percent of the total CAD 7,500 lump sum transfer. This extra spending covered a diverse range of categories: 54 percent more on transit, 113 percent more on clothing, 34 percent more on food, and so on. Of the treatment groups, the cash group increased its expenditure on alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes by the smallest proportion (11 percent).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:alcohol&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:alcohol&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It also increased its expenditure on food and clothing for the children of recipients by the largest proportion (171 percent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;code-button&quot; id=&quot;button2&quot; onclick=&quot;f2()&quot;&gt;▶ Click to show code&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;code-cell&quot; id=&quot;asset_code_2&quot; style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
# Construct data from report.
raw = pd.read_csv(&quot;new_leaf_homeless_expenditures.csv&quot;)
raw.set_index('spending_category', inplace=True)
# Sum food and clothing categories.
food_clothes_kids = raw.loc[['Food for kids', 'Clothes for kids']].sum()
food_clothes_self = raw.loc[['Food', 'Clothes']].sum()
spending = raw.drop([&quot;Food&quot;, &quot;Clothes&quot;, &quot;Food for kids&quot;, &quot;Clothes for kids&quot;])
spending.loc[&quot;Food and clothes for self&quot;] = food_clothes_self
spending.loc[&quot;Food and clothes for kids&quot;] = food_clothes_kids

# Add total row and label total for graph.
spending.loc['TOTAL'] = spending.sum()
spending['is_total'] = spending.index == 'TOTAL'

spending.index.rename('Category', inplace=True)
spending['% difference'] = (
    100 * (spending.cash / spending.non_cash - 1)).round()


import plotly.graph_objects as go

# Plot % difference.
BLUE = '#1976D2'
DARK_BLUE = '#0D47A1'
COLOR_MAP = {True: DARK_BLUE, False: BLUE}  # Total vs non-total.
spending_order = spending.sort_values('% difference')
spending_order.rename({'cash': 'Cash', 'non_cash': 'Non-cash',
                       'is_total': 'Total'},
                      axis=1, inplace=True)
fig = px.bar(spending_order, y=spending_order.index, x='% difference',
             color='Total', color_discrete_map=COLOR_MAP,
             orientation='h', hover_data=['Cash', 'Non-cash'])

fig.update_layout(font=dict(family='Roboto'),
                  plot_bgcolor='white',
                  paper_bgcolor='white',
                  showlegend=False,
                  xaxis_title='Difference between cash and non-cash group',
                  yaxis_title='',
                  xaxis_ticksuffix='%',
                  yaxis={'categoryorder': 'array',
                         'categoryarray': spending_order.index},
                  title='Spending differences between cash and non-cash groups'
                  )
fig.add_layout_image(
    dict(
        source=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/UBICenter/ubicenter.org/master/assets/images/logos/wide-blue.jpg&quot;,
        # See https://github.com/plotly/plotly.py/issues/2975.
        # source=&quot;../_static/logos/wide-blue.jpg&quot;,
        xref=&quot;paper&quot;, yref=&quot;paper&quot;,
        x=1.04, y=-0.13,
        sizex=0.12, sizey=0.12,
        xanchor=&quot;right&quot;, yanchor=&quot;bottom&quot;
    )
)
fig.show(config={'displayModeBar': False})
    &lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function f2() {
  var x = document.getElementById(&quot;asset_code_2&quot;);
  var b = document.getElementById(&quot;button2&quot;);
  if (x.style.display === &quot;none&quot;) {
    x.style.display = &quot;block&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9660 Click to hide code&quot;;
  } else {
    x.style.display = &quot;none&quot;;
    b.innerHTML = &quot;&amp;#9654 Click to show code&quot;;
  }
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    $(document).ready(function(){
      $(&quot;#asset2&quot;).load(&quot;/assets/markdown_assets/canada-homelessness-experiment/2020-12-14-canada-homelessness-experiment-asset-2.html&quot;);
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;asset2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of quantifying the changes is as a share of spending. Alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes made up 9 percent of the cash group’s spending, a fifth less than the non-cash group’s 11.4 percent, while food and clothes for children made up 7.9 percent of the cash group’s spending, nearly double the 4.1 percent share in the non-cash group. The cash group also spent a larger share on clothes (for themselves) and transit, and a smaller share on rent and food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transitions-to-stable-housing&quot;&gt;Transitions to stable housing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cash recipients also spent less time homeless than the control group. The two groups started similarly, but in the month following the intervention, the cash group was only homeless for 49 percent of days, while the control group was homeless for 78 percent of those days. The effect diminished over time, and by the end of the year, the two groups converged at around a fifth of days homeless. Overall, people in the cash group spent an average of 88 fewer days homeless throughout the full year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/days_homeless_chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Days homeless fell faster over the year for the cash group than the non-cash group&quot; title=&quot;Change in days homeless for cash and non-cash groups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those extra 88 days in homelessness housing and services would have cost the government about $8,200, exceeding the $7,500 grant (NLP did not report total costs beyond the grant, which would factor into a comprehensive cost-effectiveness analysis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In open-ended surveys, cash recipients reported that they did not have to depend on social services and could move into housing that better met their preferences. For instance, one participant said, “The impact it had on my life was huge. I was able to do a lot of things that I couldn’t do before. It has changed my ability to make proper choices. If I had not received the cash transfer, I wouldn’t be able to move out. Wouldn’t be able to get my car back on the road. None of that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparison-with-other-studies&quot;&gt;Comparison with other studies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While NLP is the first randomized controlled trial giving unconditional cash transfers to people experiencing homelessness, it aligns with other studies on how cash transfers are spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diversity of NLP participants’ spending is not unusual. The NGO GiveDirectly, which distributes unconditional cash transfers to extremely poor households in East Africa, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article/131/4/1973/2468874?casa_token=r0_EGO-olVkAAAAA:D-gM7NEQ05yqBPV7qpwoDUZdQYeBkc0k0VD25VTBNDC9UAJbhM12Z45LDcGE3YRDELaGfBD7ktbJjA&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; in a randomized controlled trial that “With the exception of temptation goods (alcohol and tobacco), transfers increase expenditures in all categories, including food, medical and education expenditure, and social events.” GiveDirectly’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GDLive tool&lt;/a&gt; shows unfiltered, unedited stories from recipients of their unconditional cash transfers and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/ubi-study&quot;&gt;universal basic income&lt;/a&gt; payments; perusing the stories of UBI recipients reveals variety in spending, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/1b0ed686-5aef-4386-8fc3-0c00078d810d/199799?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;poultry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/a048e9ee-4ee3-4af4-9a95-3e3a64b2d568/199175?context=search-UBI#payment_23&quot;&gt;tea seedlings&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/6e54ba92-ddde-4634-8c8e-f092303c56e6/199793?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;school fees&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/65e70a79-f575-49e4-82e4-88bcf186e395/199033?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;dowries&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/cf2ec5ca-0fa8-4cab-98ed-3b8712ccf0e9/199064?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;water tanks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://live.givedirectly.org/newsfeed/822e173e-d163-4472-a6ac-5124a59f44d1/199001?context=search-UBI#payment_26&quot;&gt;homebuilding materials&lt;/a&gt;. A study of Australia’s Covid-19 economic support payment also found that recipients—mostly pensioners—increased spending across a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smh.com.au/business/the-economy/groceries-vs-video-games-how-women-and-men-spend-their-stimulus-payments-differently-20200419-p54l88.html&quot;&gt;diverse range of categories&lt;/a&gt;. Given many in-kind assistance programs target just one or two categories each, such as food and rent, cash can fill in gaps for other needs that might be harder for policymakers to anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending on children is especially common, as evidenced by the robust evidence that cash transfers benefit children. As we summarize in &lt;a href=&quot;https://child-allowance.ubicenter.org/empirical.html&quot;&gt;our child allowance paper&lt;/a&gt;, cash transfers consistently improve education and nutrition, as well as long-term outcomes like earnings and even lifespan, across both developing and developed countries. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w14624/w14624.pdf&quot;&gt;One study&lt;/a&gt; from Canada found that when Manitoba increased its child benefit in 2001, children ages 0 to 3 showed improved motor and social development, children ages 4-5 showed lower aggression and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common concern around giving money to poor people is that they will spend on temptation goods like alcohol, drugs, and cigarettes. This worry motivated San Francisco voters to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_Proposition_N_(2002)&quot;&gt;replace cash assistance&lt;/a&gt; for people experiencing homelessness with in-kind benefits like housing, in a 2002 program called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/politics/la-pol-ca-gavin-newsom-homelessness-san-francisco-20181023-story.html&quot;&gt;“Care Not Cash.”&lt;/a&gt; A number of studies show such concerns to be misplaced. Data from San Francisco’s pre-Care-Not-Cash days indicates that homeless cash recipients were &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1093/jurban/jti015&quot;&gt;less likely to use drugs&lt;/a&gt; than those who didn’t receive cash (they were also less likely to receive income from selling drugs or be incarcerated, and more likely to find shelter). A &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/184358/drinking-highest-among-educated-upper-income-americans.aspx&quot;&gt;2015 Gallup poll&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3185179/&quot;&gt;2011 analysis&lt;/a&gt; of the Panel Study of Income Dynamics also found that low-income people consume less alcohol than higher-income people (though they’re more likely to drink heavy quantities and similarly likely to report that they drink more than they should). A &lt;a href=&quot;http://documents1.worldbank.org/curated/en/617631468001808739/pdf/WPS6886.pdf&quot;&gt;2014 World Bank meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; demonstrates that these results are not mere correlations: data from 19 quantitative papers, including several randomized controlled trials, found that cash transfers most often &lt;em&gt;reduced&lt;/em&gt; or had no effect on temptation good consumption.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:temptation&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:temptation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada has long welcomed unconditional cash transfers, from the 1970s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200624-canadas-forgotten-universal-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;“Mincome” program&lt;/a&gt; in Manitoba to its unusually generous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/child-family-benefits/canada-child-benefit-overview.html&quot;&gt;child benefit&lt;/a&gt; to its prematurely-cancelled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/economy/making-sense/ontario-is-canceling-its-basic-income-experiment&quot;&gt;basic income pilot&lt;/a&gt; in Ontario. And as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/development/desa/dspd/wp-content/uploads/sites/22/2019/05/CASEY_Louise_Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;developed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/development/desa/dspd/wp-content/uploads/sites/22/2019/05/SPEAK_Suzanne_Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; countries tackle homelessness, discussions inevitably include cash, whether it’s San Francisco &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_Proposition_N_(2002)&quot;&gt;retracting cash assistance&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 or Manila introducing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-81-322-2160-9_15&quot;&gt;conditional cash transfer&lt;/a&gt; in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NLP unites Canadian interest in cash transfers with homelessness research. It shows that people experiencing homelessness spread lump-sum transfers over time and across spending categories—especially focusing on their children—and that cash transfers accelerate transitions into stable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions following this study remain. For example, how would cash transfers affect the &lt;a href=&quot;https://canadiancentreforaddictions.org/addiction-in-the-homeless-population/&quot;&gt;40 percent&lt;/a&gt; of Canadians experiencing homelessness who have substance abuse disorders? Or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lop.parl.ca/staticfiles/PublicWebsite/Home/ResearchPublications/InBriefs/PDF/2014-11-e.pdf&quot;&gt;similar share&lt;/a&gt; with mental illness? NLP excluded both groups from this round, though a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/370/6522/eaay0214&quot;&gt;recent Science meta-review&lt;/a&gt; found that “cash transfers and broader anti-poverty programs reduce depression and anxiety in randomized trials.” The long-term effects on children experiencing homelessness may be even starker, as the review also finds that “poverty experienced in childhood and in utero [results] in impaired cognitive development and adult mental illness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question is: how do lump sum transfers, as used in the NLP experiment, compare to recurring payments for people experiencing homelessness? Research to date on this question has largely focused on developing countries. For example, a review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odi.org/sites/odi.org.uk/files/odi-assets/publications-opinion-files/5745.pdf&quot;&gt;post-emergency aid and development&lt;/a&gt; contexts suggests that regular payments are less prone to corruption than lump sum transfers, and that they outperform on measures of social protection, while lump-sum transfers can more effectively spur investment if targeted to entrepreneurs. Similarly, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article/131/4/1973/2468874?casa_token=r0_EGO-olVkAAAAA:D-gM7NEQ05yqBPV7qpwoDUZdQYeBkc0k0VD25VTBNDC9UAJbhM12Z45LDcGE3YRDELaGfBD7ktbJjA&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly study&lt;/a&gt; among poor households in rural Kenya found: “Monthly transfers are more likely than lump-sum transfers to improve food security, whereas lump-sum transfers are more likely to be spent on durables,” and forthcoming results from its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/ubi-study/&quot;&gt;basic income experiment&lt;/a&gt; will shed more light on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond helping people currently experiencing homelessness, how can cash transfers prevent homelessness? Studies from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-ucla-anderson-forecast-20180613-story.html&quot;&gt;UCLA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zillow.com/research/homelessness-rent-affordability-22247/&quot;&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt; link housing affordability and homelessness, suggesting that (along with reducing housing costs) raising incomes via cash transfers could keep people housed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally: how much of these effects can be attributed to cash transfers compared to coaching, workshops, and other overhead, and how do these other costs affect cost-benefit analysis? This first experimental design makes it difficult to disentangle effects, but future experiments could omit other components to focus on the cash transfer, or test other components in a grid or hierarchical design. For example, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w28106&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt; on psychological well-being in rural Kenya employed a two-by-two experimental design to study the effect of cash transfers, a psychotherapy program, and the combination of the two. This revealed that, while the cash transfer improved well-being, psychotherapy did not—either by itself or in conjunction with the cash. A similar approach could quantify the effect of coaching or workshops, conditional on cash transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundations for Social Change has committed to publishing a peer-reviewed paper on this round of results, and they are raising $10 million to enroll more participants across more Canadian cities and expand research capacity. Any follow-up research is likely to improve the precision of these estimates on expenditures and housing stability, and quantify the external validity to new contexts, even if only geographic. Open questions on cash and homelessness makes this fertile ground for further research, whether from NLP or other organizations. If nothing else, this study suggests that expanding cash assistance will increase spending on diverse needs—especially of children—and accelerate transitions to stable housing, thereby improving the range of outcomes associated with homelessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cad&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;CAD 7,500 is equivalent to about USD 5,900 as of December 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cad&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:unbalanced&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Researchers did not explain their choice to have unbalanced treatment and control groups, or to give workshop access only to the cash group. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:unbalanced&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:alcohol&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5f07a92f21d34b403c788e05/t/5f751297fcfe7968a6a957a8/1601507995038/2020_09_30_FSC_Statement_of_Impact_w_Expansion.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; claims a “39% reduction in spending on alcohol, cigarettes and drugs.” In email correspondence, Foundations for Social Change clarified that this is a comparison of pre-pilot spending with that at the end of 12 months for the cash group (i.e. not compared to the non-cash group). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:alcohol&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:temptation&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Temptation goods are defined as: “goods that generate positive utility for the self that consumes them, but not for any previous self that anticipates that they will be consumed in the future.” But the meta study focuses principally on alcohol and tobacco. Similarly, the study suggests that temptation goods are synonymous with demerit goods or, “goods that were so demeritorious (either to the consumer or to others) that the government may be correct in regulating their use. That term is sometimes used in reference to alcohol and tobacco in cash transfer studies.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:temptation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>[&quot;charles&quot;, &quot;max&quot;]</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="canada" />
      
        <category term="homelessness" />
      
        <category term="pilots" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Recipients spent mostly on their children and stable housing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What we learned about basic income in 2019</title>
      <link href="/what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What we learned about basic income in 2019" />
      <published>2020-01-01T07:58:02+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-01T07:58:02+00:00</updated>
      <id>/what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019">&lt;p&gt;2019 has been a big year for universal basic income (UBI). Web searches for the topic rose over 40 percent since 2018 in the US, and over 130 percent globally. A 2019 Nobel laureate wrote a paper on &lt;a href=&quot;https://economics.mit.edu/files/16000&quot;&gt;UBI in the developing world&lt;/a&gt;, the World Bank published a book of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/books/edition/_/00XEDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;UBI evidence&lt;/a&gt;, and Palgrave Macmillan published the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palgrave.com/gp/book/9783030143770&quot;&gt;fifteenth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palgrave.com/gp/book/9783030236137&quot;&gt;sixteenth&lt;/a&gt; books in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palgrave.com/gp/series/14981&quot;&gt;academic series on UBI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-01-01-what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019-0.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post reviews a slice of the UBI-related research that came out this year. It begins with evaluations of UBI programs and experiments, then considers simulations of UBI policy, followed by studies of related programs like cash transfers, and finally how the public feels about UBI and cash transfers (and what affects those sentiments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ubi-programs&quot;&gt;UBI programs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of new studies came out on the Alaska Permanent Fund Dividend (PFD), which pays residents between $1,000 and $3,000 per year from returns on oil wealth. Guettabi’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarworks.alaska.edu/xmlui/bitstream/handle/11122/10581/2019_05_20-EffectsOfAKPFD.pdf?sequence=1&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of research to date summarizes the null effect on employment, positive effects on birthweight and consumption of non-durable goods (e.g. food, not cars) and services, and reductions of childhood obesity and poverty; the review also showed increased income inequality. Feinberg and Keuhn found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://editorialexpress.com/cgi-bin/conference/download.cgi?db_name=IIOC2019&amp;amp;paper_id=40&quot;&gt;entrepreneurship rose&lt;/a&gt; after the PFD’s introduction, though the effect faded. The PFD increased &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.iseralaska.org/media/7c5b42d2-02b3-46dc-8221-5d32776ec51f/Universal_Cash_and_Crime.pdf&quot;&gt;substance abuse&lt;/a&gt; incidents, had no effect on violent crime, and reduced property crime (Watson et al; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.westminster.ac.uk/sites/default/public-files/general-documents/WPS%202019_02_Dorsett%20R.pdf&quot;&gt;Dorsett&lt;/a&gt; also found reduced property crime, but only when the PFD payouts were large). Lerner found no detectable effect of the PFD on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.04083.pdf&quot;&gt;high school completion&lt;/a&gt;. Mahdavi goes back to the PFD’s introduction in 1976, finding that receiving the PFD just before an election &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paashamahdavi.com/LBP-aug2019.pdf&quot;&gt;reduces voter turnout&lt;/a&gt; compared to receiving it just afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://julkaisut.valtioneuvosto.fi/bitstream/handle/10024/161361/Report_The%20Basic%20Income%20Experiment%2020172018%20in%20Finland.pdf&quot;&gt;Finland’s UBI experiment&lt;/a&gt; had no effect on employment, but significantly improved each of 14 questions asked about well-being, from trust to confidence to health, and raised appetite for UBI. The Stockton Economic Empowerment Demonstration (SEED) launched a &lt;a href=&quot;https://seed.sworps.tennessee.edu/employment.html&quot;&gt;dashboard&lt;/a&gt; characterizing the recipients and comparison groups, but no experiment results yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simulations&quot;&gt;Simulations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoynes and Rothstein &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w25538&quot;&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt; in February that “UBI pilot studies will do little to resolve the major outstanding questions,” and that design questions — for example, how it’s funded and what it replaces — deserve more attention. Researchers started to answer that call throughout the year, simulating full UBIs, UBIs for children, and smaller UBIs funded by fees on carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ubi-simulations&quot;&gt;UBI simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple researchers, myself included, simulated presidential candidate Andrew Yang’s Freedom Dividend, a UBI of $1,000 per month per adult funded by a 10 percent VAT and other sources. The Committee for a Responsible Federal Budget found that a 10 percent VAT &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crfb.org/blogs/would-10-vat-pay-1000-month-ubi&quot;&gt;would be insufficient&lt;/a&gt; to fund a $1,000 UBI. I too found that Yang’s plan would add to the deficit, though it would &lt;a href=&quot;distributional-analysis-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend&quot;&gt;dramatically reduce poverty and inequality&lt;/a&gt;. I also simulated a &lt;a href=&quot;budget-neutral-version-of-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend&quot;&gt;budget-neutral version&lt;/a&gt; of the plan (closer to $500 per month), which would still be distributionally progressive, and found that the citizenship limitation is the &lt;a href=&quot;why-some-low-income-people-come-out-behind-in-andrew-yangs-freedom-dividend&quot;&gt;main reason&lt;/a&gt; some low-income people are left worse off. Pomerleau found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://taxfoundation.org/andrew-yang-value-added-tax&quot;&gt;raising the VAT to 22 percent and reducing the amount to $750&lt;/a&gt; would make it budget-neutral. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ubicalculator.com/&quot;&gt;UBI Calculator&lt;/a&gt; was released, showing that Yang’s plan would add to the deficit but benefit most citizens, especially low-income ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katz and Sarel simulated a &lt;a href=&quot;https://euiha41fnsb2lyeld3vkc37i-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Basic-Income-in-Israel.pdf&quot;&gt;UBI in Israel&lt;/a&gt; funded by (a) higher income taxes and (b) ending welfare programs and tax benefits. Their plan provided monthly amounts between $340 and $930 per adult, with amount rising with age, and between $40 and $190 per child, depending on the child’s birth number in the family. They found that this plan would reduce inequality and improve work incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-01-01-what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019-1.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lansley and Reed modeled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.compassonline.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Compass_BasicIncomeForAll_2019.pdf&quot;&gt;two versions of a UBI for the UK&lt;/a&gt;: one funded by tax and benefit changes, and the other funded by a social wealth fund. They find that “a basic income even at modest levels would be highly progressive, reduce poverty and inequality, and cut dependency on means testing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-01-01-what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019-2.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plá et al found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.euromod.ac.uk/sites/default/files/working-papers/em8-19.pdf&quot;&gt;replacing Spain’s existing benefit system&lt;/a&gt; with a budget-neutral UBI would be modestly regressive, and Gentilini and Rigolini &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubdocs.worldbank.org/en/103921528839429277/SSN-Day8-1pm-Ugo-UBI.pdf&quot;&gt;found the same&lt;/a&gt; with respect to Russia and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colombino reviewed &lt;a href=&quot;https://wol.iza.org/articles/is-unconditional-basic-income-viable-alternative-to-other-social-welfare-measures/long&quot;&gt;10 simulation studies&lt;/a&gt; of UBI and negative income taxes (NITs) from multiple countries (as well as 11 non-simulation studies), finding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the evaluation criterion goes beyond labor supply effects (e.g. takes into account the effects on inequality and on the values of non-market activities), NIT and UBI in most cases turn out to be superior to the current systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;child-allowance-simulations&quot;&gt;Child allowance simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Child allowances are UBIs for children; they exist in some form in many countries, and the US has considered reforms to create one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant US child assistance proposal is the American Family Act (AFA), which would reform the Child Tax Credit to eliminate the phase-in and increase the amount. This would create a near-child allowance, excluding only high earners. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.povertycenter.columbia.edu/news-internal/2019/3/5/the-afa-and-child-poverty&quot;&gt;Collyer et al&lt;/a&gt; found “that the AFA would move 4 million children out of poverty and cut deep poverty among children in half,” with the phase-in removal being particularly important for poverty reduction. Hammond and Orr arrive at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.expandthechildtaxcredit.com/the-american-family-act&quot;&gt;similar conclusion&lt;/a&gt;, while also finding that the AFA would reduce adult poverty by 10 percent and that its average benefit would be higher for non-white families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wunder found that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00213624.2019.1603769&quot;&gt;$9,330 annual child allowance&lt;/a&gt; would reduce US child poverty by 75 percent, and CANCEA found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://ubiworks.ca/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/Economic-Contribution-of-the-Canada-Child-Benefit.pdf&quot;&gt;Canada would have 588,000 more children in poverty&lt;/a&gt; if not for their Child Benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;carbon-dividend-simulations&quot;&gt;Carbon dividend simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon dividends are carbon fees whose revenue is distributed as an unconditional cash transfer, i.e. as a (small) UBI. Several carbon pricing bills are in the US Congress, but only one fully rebates the revenue as a UBI: the Energy Innovation and Carbon Dividend Act (EICDA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaufman et al found that the EICDA would reduce emissions and air pollution, and also would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://energypolicy.columbia.edu/research/report/assessment-energy-innovation-and-carbon-dividend-act&quot;&gt;highly progressive&lt;/a&gt;. Hafstead found that the EICDA would be a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rff.org/cpc/&quot;&gt;net financial gain&lt;/a&gt; for the bottom three quintiles (on average) and reduce annual emissions by 53 percent by 2035, though it would also reduce GDP by 2.5 percent by 2035.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2020-01-01-what-we-learned-about-basic-income-in-2019-3.jpg#layoutTextWidth&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related-programs&quot;&gt;Related programs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;givedirectly-cash-transfers&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly cash transfers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://givedirectly.org&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; is a charity that provides unconditional cash transfers (UCTs) to extremely poor families, mostly in East Africa. They were founded by economists and continue to study the effect of their work in randomized controlled trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their most newsworthy paper, released in December, examined the general equilibrium effects of their transfers. In this experiment, entire villages were treated, with transfers restricted to low-income households. Egger et al found that &lt;a href=&quot;http://emiguel.econ.berkeley.edu/assets/miguel_research/88/GE-Paper_2019-12-18.pdf&quot;&gt;non-recipients also benefited&lt;/a&gt;: households receiving the transfers saw consumption rise, but so did households in the same village who didn’t get the money — and their consumption rose a similar amount. Each dollar of cash transfers grew the local economy by $2.60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other studies also found substantial benefits from the GiveDirectly UCTs. Haushofer et al found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.princeton.edu/~joha/publications/Haushofer_Ringdal_Shapiro_Wang_IPV_2019-07-13_jh.pdf&quot;&gt;UCTs reduce intimate partner violence&lt;/a&gt;, with larger benefits when given to women; like Egger, they find spillovers, with violence toward non-recipient women in treated villages falling nearly as much as for recipient women. In another paper, Haushofer et al found that UCTs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.princeton.edu/~joha/publications/Haushofer_Reisinger_Shapiro_Inequality_2019.pdf&quot;&gt;worsen psychological well-being for non-recipients&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, Cooke et al find &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/Cash_Crop_Ugandan_CoffeeRCT.pdf&quot;&gt;significant increases in consumption and revenue&lt;/a&gt; for coffee farmer recipients of GiveDirectly UCTs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly will release results from their universal basic income experiment next year; the 2019 Nobel laureate Abhijit Banerjee is researching it. They also published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/basic-income/&quot;&gt;guide to UBI&lt;/a&gt; this year, which includes relevant academic research and their planned contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-cash-transfers&quot;&gt;Other cash transfers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carneiro et al found that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.homepages.ucl.ac.uk/~uctpimr/research/CDGP.pdf&quot;&gt;providing extremely poor Nigerian families UCTs&lt;/a&gt; from pregnancy until the child turned 2, combined with pre- and neo-natal information, reduced children’s stunting by 8 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracing Mexican families 20 years after their receipt of a conditional cash transfer (CCT), Aguilar et al found &lt;a href=&quot;http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/423621568052375850/pdf/Long-Term-Effects-of-PROSPERA-on-Welfare.pdf&quot;&gt;positive effects&lt;/a&gt; on household formation, migration, durable assets, consumption expenditures and food security, and intergenerational mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baird et al evaluated a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gps.ucsd.edu/_files/faculty/mcintosh/mcintosh_research_when-the-money-runs-out.pdf&quot;&gt;two-year CCT-UCT experiment&lt;/a&gt; for adolescent females in Malawi, finding that the CCT caused sustained improvements on education and fertility (having children when they want to). While the UCT did not cause sustained benefits among recipients, it improved fertility and reduced HIV infections in the short term, and improved health of the recipients’ children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daidone et al reviewed evaluations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/ajae/article/101/5/1401/5420281&quot;&gt;government cash transfer programs in seven countries in sub-Saharan Africa&lt;/a&gt;, which show consistently positive effects on consumption and moving workers from casual agricultural wage labor to more productive work on family farms or elsewhere, though other effects varied by country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;universality-and-unconditionality&quot;&gt;Universality and unconditionality&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New research compares the traditional means testing and requirements to the universality and unconditionality of UBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kidd and Athias examined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.developmentpathways.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Hit-and-Miss-March13-1.pdf&quot;&gt;38 programs across 23 low- and middle-income countries&lt;/a&gt;, finding that the four universal programs were significantly more effective at reaching the poor than means-tested programs, mistakenly excluding under 10 percent of its intended audience, compared to exclusion errors above 50 percent in most means-tested programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ILO and UNICEF published a report &lt;a href=&quot;https://reliefweb.int/sites/reliefweb.int/files/resources/wcms_669336.pdf&quot;&gt;advocating universal child grants&lt;/a&gt; across countries as a tool of meeting the UN’s goal of ending global poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuert et al reviewed the behavioral economics literature in their paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ideas42.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/ideas42-Work-Requirements-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;Work Requirements Don’t Work&lt;/a&gt;. Harris studied the &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.upjohn.org/up_workingpapers/297/&quot;&gt;US SNAP program&lt;/a&gt; (food stamps) specifically, finding that “work requirements significantly decreased SNAP participation and marginally increased employment for ABAWD [Able-Bodied Adults without Dependents].”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sentiment&quot;&gt;Sentiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, a Hill-HarrisX poll found &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/hilltv/rising/463055-more-voters-support-universal-basic-income&quot;&gt;rising support&lt;/a&gt; for a $1,000 per month UBI to help Americans whose jobs are threatened by automation, from 43 percent in February to 49 percent in September; it is especially popular with voters under age 35 and Democrats. Echelon Insights &lt;a href=&quot;http://echeloninsights.com/wp-content/uploads/Omnibus-June-2019_Policies.pdf&quot;&gt;asked voters&lt;/a&gt; about UBI without the automation framing, emphasizing its unconditionality, and found that 40 percent supported it; they too found higher support among Democrats and young people, as well as those with lower incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late Alan Krueger conducted a &lt;a href=&quot;https://healthpolicy.usc.edu/evidence-base/what-do-americans-think-about-universal-basic-income/&quot;&gt;survey experiment&lt;/a&gt;, asking Americans whether they support (a) a UBI in the US, and (b) a UBI in poor parts of Africa, randomizing the order of (a) and (b). Respondents who were asked first about UBI in Africa were more favorable to UBI in the US, and those who were asked first about UBI in the US were less favorable to UBI in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stadelmann-Steffen and Dermont identified &lt;a href=&quot;https://boris.unibe.ch/135192/1/JSP-StadelmannSteffenDermont2019.pdf&quot;&gt;greater UBI support in Finland&lt;/a&gt; than in Switzerland, with people in both countries favoring UBIs that are (a) more generous, and (b) restricted to citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminiscently of both Krueger’s survey experiment and Mahdavi’s PFD paper, Mosec and Mo conducted a &lt;a href=&quot;http://ebrary.ifpri.org/utils/getfile/collection/p15738coll2/id/133270/filename/133484.pdf&quot;&gt;survey experiment in Pakistan&lt;/a&gt;, finding that cash transfers increase support for political leaders and institutions only when they are primed to think of inequality (salience of inequality also reduces political support among those denied cash transfers). Similarly, Zucco et al conducted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00220388.2019.1577388&quot;&gt;survey experiments in Brazil and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; finding that “conditional transfers are only marginally more popular than similar unconditional transfers in nationally representative samples, but that this difference is substantially larger among the better-off and among those primed to think of themselves as different from beneficiaries.” Finally, Rios et al &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/disa.12378&quot;&gt;also show&lt;/a&gt; that “residents of Fiji who received a post‐disaster cash transfer are up to 20 per cent more likely to be very satisfied with the government than are those who did not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are some common threads from UBI research in 2019? New evidence from Alaska, Finland, and developing countries find that UBIs and cash transfers have generally similar effects: positive effects on consumption and children’s health, and on incomes in developing countries. UCTs in Kenya had positive economic spillovers but negative psychological spillovers, which may also be evident in Pakistan. Simulated UBIs were regressive when only replacing means-tested programs, but progressive when other funding sources were included, and various studies found that universal transfers can better reach the poor. Finally, UBI appears to be getting more popular, though its reception varies by country and framing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important evidence on UBI in 2020 may come from GiveDirectly’s UBI experiment in Kenya, which is randomized by village and guarantees recipients transfers for up to 12 years. But if it’s anything like 2019, we’ll have much more research to look forward to, as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Max Ghenis</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="pilots" />
      
        <category term="external research" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The research frontier expanded rapidly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
